[MUSIC]
理論的建構
In this lecture, we'll talk about theory construction.
這一講談的是理論的建構
In most of the course, we talked about statistical inferences,
之前大部分課程都是談根據資料做統計推論
drawing inferences from data.
But of course, what we really want to know is whether your theory is true or
不過做研究都是要知道理論能不能正確預測結果
not and can predict something.
Generating a good theory is difficult, and
建構好理論不是容易的事
it depends a little bit on the specific research area are you working.
需要依靠個人在特定領域的研究心得
But we can give some general recommendations.
接著我會給一些廣泛性的建議
Now in most of this course we've been talking about statistical hypothesis and
我們已經談了很多統計假設與推論的方法
drawing statistical inferences.
But as a researcher of course what you want to do is draw theoretical inferences.
不過研究者最想做的是理論推測
To do this, you of course first have to have a good theory
首先當然是有一個好理論
that you can use to create a statistical hypothesis.
再根據理論創造統計假設
So we see that statistical inferences and
因此統計推論
theory generation are basically two sides of the same coin.
和理論建的建構可說是一體兩面
A scientific theory is a set of testable statements about the relation between
科學理論是根據資料的可證宣言集合
observations.
And whenever we collect data, we do so
只要手上有合適的資料
with the goal to test some of these statements, to try to make an inference
目的就是檢驗這些宣言，藉此推論
about whether the theory has good predictive power or not.
理論是否有充分的預測能力
Now we focus a lot on testing these theories but
之前談的都是理論的檢驗
not a lot of theory construction.
較少談理論的建構
This is an important topic in itself.
建構本身就是一個重要主題
Sometimes more difficult to teach.
有些內容難以言傳
But it's really important to keep in mind that theories are really what's driving
然而理論是驅動科學家做研究的重要目標
the goal of doing research.
I'll give some suggestions on how to come up with good
以下提供如何提出良好理論預測的建議
ideas to generate theoretical predictions.
Some of these are based on this book, Theory Construction and
一些是出自投影片裡的這本書
Model-Building Skills,
which focuses a lot on how to do this within the social sciences.
這本書談很多社會科學理論的建構
So if you're interested in this topic,
如果你對此主題有興趣
I would highly recommend that you take a look at this book.
建議找這本書來讀一讀
So which approaches can we use?
要怎麼給你建議呢？
One used approach in science is to come up with a thought experiment.
一種方式是進行思想實驗
A very well known thought experiment is done by Einstein when he asks himself,
愛因斯坦曾提出一則著名的思想實驗
what would you see if you could travel at the speed of light?
若我能以光速前進，會看到什麼呢？
So by coming up with this though experiment and thinking about what would
由你來做這思想實驗的話，會預期發生什麼事？
happen, you can create theoretical predictions that are testable.
你能想到任何可測試的理論預測嗎？
Another approach that we use in the social sciences is sometimes
社會科學建構理論的另一個方式
to rely on your personal experiences.
是從個人經驗取材
What happens to you, and can you come up with a theoretical prediction based
你能夠從週遭的人事物發現可行的理論預測嗎？
on something that someone tells you?
One example is Stanley Milgram's mother.
有個例子來自Stanley Milgram的岳母
Over dinner, she complained that nobody in public transport would give up their seats
有天吃晚餐時，她抱怨坐公車時沒人讓座給她
if she entered the public bus.
So Stanley Milgram was interested in the social norms in cities and
Milgram因此好奇大城市裡人們的行為常態
he looked at whether people would actually give up their seats depending on how you
想了解是不是對乘客提出要求
就會有人讓座
asked these questions.
想了解是不是對乘客提出要求
就會有人讓座
He found the 56% of the people actually would give up their seat if you
他研究後發現有56%的乘客會在知道要求後會讓座
nicely asked.
Another approach is to try to empathize with other people.
還有一種方式是發揮對他人的同理心
Put yourself in someone else's shoes and
如同諺語“給自己穿上別人的鞋子”
think, what drives the behavior of this individual?
理解他人行為之後的想法
In psychology, a well known example of this is the question,
心理學的一個著名案例是
how it is possible that people who worked in concentration camps did what they did?
探討人們在集中營裡生活和工作的行為模式
This inspired a lot of theory development on authority, for example.
這個案例促成權威理論的發展
You can also use observations.
觀察也是建構理論的方式
Let's say you go out and you buy a car and
像是出門買汽車
you look at the car salesman, what do these people do to sell you a car?
你可以觀察銷售員如何與你互動
What kind of ticks do they use and how can this inform you about persuasion and
他們用什麼技巧打動你
脫服你買車
theories about how to make
more persuasive arguments?
想想有什麼理論能預測有說服力的說法？
Another approach we often use is to rely on metaphors.
科學家也會利用隱喻建構理論
Now a metaphor should never be a replacement of an existing theory, but
隱喻雖然不能完全取代理論
it can be used to inspire theoretical reasoning.
但是能引起理論的思考
In memory research,
拿記憶研究來說
one of the theoretical models is the model of memory like a storage bin.
有種理論假設記憶像儲藏盒
Whatever you put in last in a storage bin is also most easily retrieved.
最後放進去的最容易被拿出來
So one theoretical prediction based on this metaphorical line of reasoning
有個參考這種隱喻的理論
could be, is it also the case in human memory that whatever we store last is most
預測最後記憶的資訊是最容易提取的
easily retrieved?
What's always a good idea as a scientist is to ask why and
很多資深科學家建議找問題要保持赤子之心
how like a three year old.
Don't take anything for granted.
不要存先入為主的想法
When you read about theories in the literature,
閱讀文獻中談到的理論
always ask, why would this be the case?
要不斷地問，為什麼是這樣子
What's going on?
還能變成什麼樣？
What's the underlying mechanism?
有什麼潛在的機制？
And this can inspire new theoretical questions.
這些問法能引發新的理論觀點
Finally, a good idea is to have broad interest as a scientist.
最後的建議是保持廣泛的興趣
We see that many of the most ground breaking ideas come from
很多突破性的創見是來自
introducing ideas in other scientific disciplines into your own research line.
從其他科學領域引進的觀點
You don't have to limit yourself to other scientific disciplines.
不要限制自己對其他科學領域的好奇心
You can also be inspired by movies or books or whatever you see and hear.
一部電影，一本書，任何聽聞都有可能帶來靈感
Now after you have generated some hypothesis and
建構理論預測之後
some theory, it's good to try to formalize this theory and
最好儘可能將理論與預測模式化
this theoretical prediction as well as possible.
One idea is to use multiple modalities to do so.
可以使用各式各樣的媒介
So you can use words to describe your theory, figures and numbers.
像是文字、圖像、數字都能做描述媒介
For example, let's say we have the theoretical hypothesis that
例如有個理論假設
students are happier than teachers, but especially on hot days.
學生比老師的快樂感高，尤其是大熱天
The idea being that on these hot days, students are free to go out and
理論的說法是學生在大熱天能自由外出
enjoy the weather while teachers are,
但是老師卻要在室內改作業和備課等等
of course, working inside, preparing your next lecture or grading your assignments.
So we can visualize this in the form of a simple graph.
這樣的預測可以用簡單的圖像表達
We can have a statistical hypothesis saying that this is ANOVA and
像是一個用ANOVA檢驗交互作用的統計假設
we should find an interaction.
Or you can even try to specify the numbers that you expect to observe in each of
或者設定兩種天氣的老師和學生的平均感受值
the conditions in this design.
When you define your theoretical prediction, it's always good to
設定理論預測時
think about the boundary conditions of the effect that you predict.
設定理論預測的可行情境是有幫助的
It's very rare, at least in psychology,
至少在心理學
to have a universal theory of some sort of effect.
很少有理論能預測所有可能的效果
There are always boundary conditions.
總是只有部分可行情境能被預測
You should not make statement that generalizes over
宣稱任何事都可預測是不切實際的
everything that's possible.
One thing you can try to do is think when would actually the opposite while
你可以試想有什麼情境是我的理論無法預測
I'm predicting being true?
McGuire challenges readers to think about the situation that every proposition
McGuire給了這麼一道建議
請你想想在什麼情況下
is occasionally true, at least in certain contexts viewed from certain perspectives.
你的理論在那種觀點關注的脈絡中，
所有命題會是正確的
He calls this perspectivism.
這種想法稱為觀點主義
His idea is that it always depends.
中心思想是觀察事物所根據的觀點
So whatever theory you have, it might be true, but
你現在想到的理論或許是對的
it always depends on certain context.
但只限在指定的脈絡中
And he even goes as far as to say that the opposite
McGuire還指出在某些情況
與理論預測相反的結果也可能為真
of any theoretical prediction is also true depending on situations.
McGuire還指出在某些情況
與理論預測相反的結果也可能為真
So try to define these boundary conditions in this context as well as possible when
所以設定可行情境的脈絡要儘可能
you make a theoretical prediction.
與理論預測一致
Fiedler distinguishes between two
parts in the scientific cycle.
Fiedler區別科學流程的兩個部分
A loosening stage, where we generate theoretical ideas, and
建構理論的寬鬆階段
a tightening stage where we select and test the best of these ideas.
以及選擇與測試理論的緊要階段
Now when we're in the loosening stage,
寬鬆階段時的思考
you have to create as much random variation as possible.
要儘可能地做發散式創造
Anything goes.
想出所有可能性
Whatever helps you to generate good theoretical ideas goes.
任可能建構理論預測的想法都可接受
So you can play around with data, explore, come up with crazy ideas.
儘情地玩弄資料、探索與思考瘋狂的點子
And that's all fine.
都是可行的手段
Only later in the tightening stage comes the part of the process where we think
稍後的緊要階段就要評估想出來的點子到底好不好？
okay, which of these IDs that we generated was actually good?
Which should we reject and which can we use to keep going?
那些要捨棄？那些可保留？
You can think of what a theory would really imply,
最終版理論的預測內容
come up with as many as possible ideas of what the theoretical prediction actually
要儘可能觸及在文獻中讀到的任何狀況
is when you read about something in the literature, for example.
You can play around with methods.
你可以嘗試任何方法
If you have some sort of measurement device,
要是你有某種測量工具
try to use it in all sorts of different ways.
在各種可測量的狀況都試試看
You can also play around with data.
也可以嘗試各種探索資料的角度
You might even simulate data to see what would happen
像是根據某種假設模擬資料
depending on specific assumptions, and then subsequently use the ideas that
歸納出可行的模擬結果
come from these simulations to test them on people.
再使用實際的樣本收集資料
Or you can explore existing data sets.
或者從已存在的資料挖掘
Now of course we've talked about how exploring data sets can increase the type
之前已經提到很多探索資料會增加型一錯誤率的問題
one error rates.
But here, we're not talking about the testing stage,
但這不是理論的檢定
not the tightening stage of theory testing.
也不是建構理論的緊要階段
We're talking about generating ideas and anything goes.
建構理論時任何可行的方法都可接受
So if you look at data sets and you can come up with a very good
探索資料能有助發想好的理解預測
theoretical prediction, that's perfectly fine.
可以放手去做
Of course, after generating this idea, you actually want to move on to the tightening
當然，有了夠多想法之後，
緊要階段就要挑出可行的想法
stage and see whether this idea actually holds.
當然，有了夠多想法之後，
緊要階段就要挑出可行的想法
But that's a different function.
緊要階段的思考模式不同之前
It comes later in the scientific cycle.
科學流程的工作模式都是由鬆入緊
Now in this lecture, we've talked about generating theoretical ideas.
這一講談了如何建構理論的建議
Throughout the course, we mainly focus on drawing valid statistical inferences.
之前的每一講主要討論有效的統計推論
But you cannot draw good statistical inferences without having a good theory.
但是沒有好的理論就沒有好的統計推論
So theory construction and generating valid theoretical predictions
建構理論與有效的預測
is just as important as statistical inferences,
和統計推論是同樣重要的
although it might be more difficult to teach.
雖然理論的建構很難教授
It's important to keep in mind that a good theory and
好的研究者要時時記住好理論
good statistical inferences are two sides of the same coin.
與好的統計推論是一體兩面
[MUSIC]
影片結束